today we are going to talk about a
framework that is called electron and
we're going to see how electron allows
us to make cross-platform desktop
applications for mac os linux and
windows using only html css and
javascript
many many companies use electron to make
cross-platform desktop applications so
it's very very likely that you are using
or have used already an application that
is built using electron the desktop
application for slack for example is
built using electron github desktop is
also built using electron plus react and
typescript the design tool sigma skype
by microsoft the windows and mac os
applications for twitch are all built
using electron the facebook messenger
desktop application is also built using
electron and the desktop application for
discord is also an electron app as you
can see very big names in very big
companies are choosing electron to make
their desktop application but nothing is
more mind-blowing in my opinion than
knowing that the most used developer
tool is also built using electron and
that tool is visual studio code many
people don't know this but visual studio
code is built using electron and
typescript so how does electron actually
work electron uses node.js to talk to
the operative system of the user and it
uses chromium to render the user
interface that the user will be
interacting with when an electron
application starts nodejs will talk to
the operative system to start a chromium
process and create a browser window it's
here in the browser window where our
html css and javascript is going to run
chromium is an open source web browser
that is the core is the engine of things
like google chrome brave browser
microsoft edge and even naver whale so
basically when we start a electron
application what we are starting is like
a google chrome window a browser window
but without the navigation bar
but also because electron uses node.js
to talk to the operative system we are
able to make our browser window feel
like a desktop application we can create
our own menu bar or we can add keyboard
shortcuts to our application we can
access the file system and the disk of
the user in a way that a website is not
able to we can use notifications we can
show progress bars we can even take
screenshots we can hide the application
in the status bar we can run it in the
background among many other things so
now let's take a look and see how easy
it is to create our own cross platform
desktop application using electron now
before you create your desktop
application you have to have a web
application you have to have the html
the css and the javascript the web
application that i'm going to turn into
a desktop application is this one right
here this is the app that we build in
the free javascript course that we have
in our website that course is a free
eight hour course made up of 60 videos
that is going to teach you the basics of
javascript and will show you how to
build an application just like this one
you will learn how to make a login
screen a clock a to-do list a dynamic
background how to access geolocation how
to get weather information among many
many other things if you want to learn
how to build this application then
please click the link below and i will
see you there the course is 100 for free
forever so let's get started turning
this web app into a desktop
here we have the html css and javascript
files that make up our web application
that we're going to turn into a desktop
application to get started we're going
to create a new node.js project and
we're going to install electron
then in our package.json we create a
start script that is going to call
electron on the main that js file we
also create the file as well in the
main.js file we will import electron and
we're going to create a function that is
going to create a new browser window and
it's going to load the index.html file
then when the application is ready we
are going to call the function and if we
run npm run start
we can see our website is now running
inside of a desktop application to
customize the menu bar of my application
i will create an array and there i will
create two menus one with a label of the
name of my application and the second
one will have a label of a pizza emoji
then i will import menu from electron
and i will set the application menu to
the custom menu that i created and as
you can see when my application starts
we now have two menus that are both
empty but are the menus that i created
as you can see it says electron instead
of momentum but that will change when we
build our app for publishing now we will
add some system submenus to our first
menu and some custom submenus to our
pizza menu
then when the application runs
as we would see
we now have some default system submenus
and the custom submenus that we added to
our pizza menu now we can tell electron
that when somebody clicks on the new
background label we want to run the get
background function that was in our
initial javascript files and also when
somebody clicks on the reset preferences
menu i want to clear the local storage
and i want to reload the window now when
the application starts i will be able to
use it normally i will write my name and
i will write my first to-do list of the
day
now i can go to the menu and i can
request a new background as you can see
it will work just well or i can click on
reset preferences and that is going to
restart the application from zero
to build my application to make it ready
to publish i will install electron forge
and i will run the import command
now on my package.json i will add some
configurations like the product name for
my program name and i will change the
icon of my program so when it's built is
built using the icon that i want the one
i chose is the javascript logo
after this i run mpm run make and that
is going to create an executable that i
can run on my mac and i can send that to
my friends
if we go and look at what we get as a
result we are able to open that as an
application
i can also drag and drop that
application into my applications folder
and i can use it now as any other
application in my mac os
and that's it that's all we had to do as
you can see is not hard at all all we
have to do is take html css javascript
write a little bit of node.js and
electron will do its magic we can build
applications and compile them to
whatever operative system we want
electron such an amazing and cool tool
now you became more powerful as a
javascript developer you can now make
desktop applications it's crazy the
amount of power that is at our
fingertips if we learn javascript we can
make websites we can make servers we can
make native applications for ios and
android we can make video games and now
we can make desktop applications for
windows mac os and linux it's crazy the
return of investment that we get if we
learn javascript as developers we can
apply our skills in so many different
areas so if you want to learn javascript
and you want to do it for free please
click the link below and i will see you
there thank you so much for watching
this video let me know in the comments
what do you think about electron are you
surprised at how easy it is to make
desktop apps i am it's crazy also let me
know have you built a desktop
application do you want to build a
desktop application do you have any idea
let me know in the comments as well
should we make a tutorial on electron
should i make a course on electron
making something a little bit more
complex we'll see let me know in the
comments i'm gonna be looking at them
right now thank you so much for watching
stay healthy stay happy stay free eat
kimchi come send me down san angelo see
you on the next one
bye